<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on संस्कारे विश्वासटिप्पणयः</title>
    <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/shaktiH/meta/MT_lekhAH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on संस्कारे विश्वासटिप्पणयः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
	<atom:link href="https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/shaktiH/meta/MT_lekhAH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>ChinnamastA</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/shaktiH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-04-17_chinnamasta/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/shaktiH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-04-17_chinnamasta/</guid>
      <description>OM ChinnamastA mahAvidyA mahAbhImA mahodarI /
chaNDeshvarI chaNDa-mAtA chaNDa-muNDa-prabha~njinI // 4 //
OM one with a severed head, the great vidyA, the terrible one, one with a great belly;
the terrible goddess, the frightful mother, the smasher of the demons chaNDa and muNDa.
mahAchaNDA chaNDa-rUpA chaNDikA chaNDa-khaNDinI /
krodhinI krodha-jananI krodha-rUpA kuhU kalA // 5 //
Most terrifying, of terrible form, the terrifying one, the slaughterer of chaNDa;
the wrathful one, the generator of wrath, of form of wrath, of form of the new-moon phase</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In the lap of dhUmAvatI</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/shaktiH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-12-01_in-the-lap-of-dhumavati/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/shaktiH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-12-01_in-the-lap-of-dhumavati/</guid>
      <description>The harsh cawing of the solitary crow at night announces her presence. Of large size with dishevelled hair she roams. The severed heads of viShNu and rudra are seen beside her. The mystic bIja graaaM is reverberating all around her. There are the senAs of the lulApamukhas around her commanded by the dreaded kAlavAhanavadana. Beside her sits her fair daughter rakta-jyeShThA or upa-dhUmrA. Her pArshadhas are yelling hideous statements like without shivA, shiva is but a shava.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>karNamoTini vidyA</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/shaktiH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-12-08_karnamotini-vidya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/shaktiH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-12-08_karnamotini-vidya/</guid>
      <description>oM chaNDAyai namaH| oM ghaNDAyai namaH| oM karAlyai namaH| oM sumukhyai namaH| oM durmukhyai namaH| oM revatyai namaH| oM prathamAyai namaH| oM ghorAyai namaH|
vayu-tattvAtmikAyai namaH|| iti vayu maNDalaM
mama shatrUn shoShaya shoShaya |
oM saumyAyai namaH| oM bhiShaNyai namaH| oM jayAyai namaH| oM vijayAyai namaH| oM ajitAyai namaH| oM aparAjitAyai namaH| oM mahAkoTyai namaH| oM raudryai namaH|
rupa-tejas-tattvAtmikAyai namaH|| iti rupa-teja maNDalaM
mama shatrUn vidrAvaya vidrAvaya |
oM virUpAkShyai namaH| oM parAyai namaH| oM divyAyai namaH| oM AkAshamAtre namaH| oM samharyai namaH| oM daMShTrAlAyai namaH| oM shuShkarevatyai namaH|</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>kubjikA and the pa~nchavaktra mahAdeva</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/shaktiH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-07-20_kubjika-and-the-panchavaktra-mahadeva/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/shaktiH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-07-20_kubjika-and-the-panchavaktra-mahadeva/</guid>
      <description>The great tradition of paschimAmnAya goddess, our hallowed mother kubjikA, had a number of streams that are now largely forgotten. One of the older streams before its standardization in the tradition of the kubjikAmata and ShaTsAhasra streams was the worship of kubjikA conjoined with the five headed shiva (distinct from the other representations where she is conjoined with shiva as navAtman (also alluded to in the saundaryalahari; while mainly devoted to kulasundarI, 34, 39 and 41 refer to kubjikA) or has paramashiva above her) .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some notes of the ShaTsAhasra tradition</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/shaktiH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-07-10_some-notes-of-the-shatsahasra-tradition/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/shaktiH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-07-10_some-notes-of-the-shatsahasra-tradition/</guid>
      <description>When in gavalkuNDa, R1 and A saved us from the pangs of hunger. R1, A and our clan had similar histories with peregrinations through the length of jambudvIpa over time in the practice and quest of the mantra-shAstra. R1’s clan had moved back recently to the Southern realms after 2.5 centuries in the land of the malla rAjas. R1 who treated us as son also opened our eyes to some remarkable matters- she us acquainted with her father, who was one the last holders of the vidyA’s of the ShaTsAhasra tradition (since R1 was cashing her brahminical check).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The AmnAya-krama for the dual worship of shArikA and tripurA</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/shaktiH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-10-21_the-amnaya-krama-for-the-dual-worship-of-sharika-and-tripura/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/shaktiH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-10-21_the-amnaya-krama-for-the-dual-worship-of-sharika-and-tripura/</guid>
      <description>Source R and I finally got to moving ahead with the initial part of laying out the formulae related to the dual worship of shArikA and tripurA that was prevalent with the Himalayan tantrics. The shArikA-tripurA krama of aghora-shiva is related in terms of the formulae to dakShiNa-mUrti virachita uddhAra-kosha, a famous work on mantra shAstra that contains most of these formulae. The aghora-shiva here is the south-face of rudra or dakShiNa-mUrti.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The bhinnayoni vidyA</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/shaktiH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-07-02_the-bhinnayoni-vidya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/shaktiH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-07-02_the-bhinnayoni-vidya/</guid>
      <description>Since I was asked of the famed bhinna yoni vidyA, which powers the mahA mAtR^ikA nyAsa I have written it down. Of course its prakaTa as pratya~NgirA needs the inter-twining with the atharvamukha, of which the bhinna yoni is itself a prakaTa rUpa. Its manifestation as parameshvarI is can be seen in the stand alone bhinna yoni vidyA, though a practioner of the bhrigu-A~Ngirasa shruti notes the deep concordance with the atharvamukha constantly.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The circle of yakShiNI-s</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/shaktiH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-08-17_the-circle-of-yakshini-s/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/shaktiH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-08-17_the-circle-of-yakshini-s/</guid>
      <description>We bow to the great goddess of the trotalottaraM and pay worship to the great throng of yakShiNI-s that emerge from her. The yakShiNI-s are of diverse forms, all very wonderful and amazing. They bear many diverse facets of knowledge — he who can acquire them all becomes sarva-vyApin. But the knowledge is not easily acquired from the yakShiNI. There are so many ways in which they slip away after it has been shown to you by her.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The mahAmantras of the urvashI prayoga and saubhAgya sarasvatI</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/shaktiH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-07-04_the-mahamantras-of-the-urvashi-prayoga-and-saubhagya-sarasvati/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/shaktiH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-07-04_the-mahamantras-of-the-urvashi-prayoga-and-saubhagya-sarasvati/</guid>
      <description>The most glorious urvashI is invoked by her mahAmantra:
oM hrIM eM | abhi na iLA yUthasya mAtA sman nadIbhir urvashI vA gR^iNAtu | oM hrIM eM | urvashI vA bR^ihad-divA gR^iNAnA .abhyUrNvAnA prabhR^ithasyAyoH | huM svAhA
The mantras of urvashI and tillotamA are unparalled in the bliss they give. The highest joys of svarga may be glimpsed by the invocation of the glorious apsaras of great power. The might of the pa~nchachoDA of the apsaras protects him from his bhrAtR^ivyas.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The mahAvidyA of karNamoTini</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/shaktiH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-12-07_the-mahavidya-of-karnamotini/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/shaktiH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-12-07_the-mahavidya-of-karnamotini/</guid>
      <description>shrI karNamoTinI devI 

Not far from the from the town of Tenali from where hailed the great jester of Vijayanagaran court, in direction of the other little town of Narasaraopetai, is the hamlet of Nandindla. It is here that my ancestors through my maternal grandmother roamed, a clan graced with number of notable shrauta sacrificers. One of that clan was a well-learned tantric had attained siddhi of numerous mantras and was deeply proficient in the mantra shAstra.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The tilottamA prayoga</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/shaktiH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-03-09_the-tilottama-prayoga/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/shaktiH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-03-09_the-tilottama-prayoga/</guid>
      <description>The bhUta tantras recommend the worship of apasaras and provide the outlines for these rites. However, their proper deployment remains unknown except to one who has mastered the true rahasyas. The mantras of the practioners of the chInAchAra are nowhere in the league of these rahasya mantras. 8 principal apsaras may be invoked with apasara maNDala though tillotamA may be offered a special sacrifice for the highest purpose. The apasaras who are invoked are:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>vArAhI dvAdashaM</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/shaktiH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-04-27_varahi-dvadasham/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/shaktiH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-04-27_varahi-dvadasham/</guid>
      <description>vArahI dvAdashaM iti mantrasya shrI ashvAnanaH R^iShiH | anuShTup ChandaH | vArAhI devatA | shrI vArahi devI prasAda siddhi dvAra sarva sa~NkaTa haraNaM jape viniyogaH ||
pa~nchamI danDanAthA cha sa~Nketa samayeshvarI /
tathA samaya-sa~NketA vArAhI potriNI shivA //
vArtAlI cha mahAsenA .apyAGYAchakreshvarI tatha /
arighnI cheti samproktaM nAma dvAdashakaM mune //
nAma-dvAdashadhAbhikhya vajra-pa~njara-madhyagaH /
sa~NkaTe duHkham-Apnoti na kadAchana mAnavaH //</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wanderings in oDDiyAna</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/shaktiH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-09-26_wanderings-in-oddiyana/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/shaktiH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-09-26_wanderings-in-oddiyana/</guid>
      <description>Long ago the great old vaiShNava wandered in the hallowed oDDiyAna pITha, when he reached an old desolate prAsada towards the evening hour. There he seated himself and concentrated ThaM bIja. Then the divine boar-faced mistress of the 5th lunar digit graced him. She of most beautiful waist appeared there with curly locks and bearing two shining tusks on her snout. Her awesome hips were draped by a most excellent blue and golden vesture and she held the still-bloody pestle with which she had smashed the skull of visha~Nga.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>