<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on संस्कारे विश्वासटिप्पणयः</title>
    <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/rudraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on संस्कारे विश्वासटिप्पणयः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
	<atom:link href="https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/rudraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>aghora bhairava prayoga</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/rudraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-12-16_aghora-bhairava-prayoga/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/rudraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-12-16_aghora-bhairava-prayoga/</guid>
      <description>When the bhairava mantras are appropriately discharged they are like arrows whizzing from the pinAka. The shatru senA is as though rushing forward when it is suddenly attacked from the flanks by flaming missile shot by the agents of rudra. Each bhairava mantra is like a shower of fatal arrows raining on them with unstoppable fury.
Meditate upon the Adi-guru, the kShatriya woman, lakShmI~nkarA, who is the founder of the lineage of teachers of the lore of the bhairava in the kali yuga, the great princess, the sister of the noble rAjan indrabhUtI.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ashvina stuti</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/rudraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-05-30_ashvina-stuti/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/rudraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-05-30_ashvina-stuti/</guid>
      <description>The adi parvan of the mahAbhArata provides a remarkable “fossilized” sUktaM to the ashvins. It comes in the 3rd chapter of the adi parvan known as the pauShya section (1.3.60 in the critical Poona edition of the mahAbhArata). This section is a particularly interesting in terms of retaining some of the archaic structures of the epic, probably coming unadulterated from the original form of the jaya epic. Its frame narrates the tale of how janamejaya, the kuru emperor, and conqueror of takShashIla came to perform his infamous sarpa yaGYa to avenge the killing of his father parIkShit by the nAga chief.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Forms of the pratya~NgirA R^ik</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/rudraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-03-05_forms-of-the-pratyangira-rik/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/rudraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-03-05_forms-of-the-pratyangira-rik/</guid>
      <description>yAm kalpayanti no arayaH krUrAm kR^ityAm vadhUm iva /
tAm brahmaNA pari nijmaH pratyak kartAram R^icchatu //
This version is seen in the R^igveda khila 4.5.1. It may be used for countering kR^ityAs via the procedure recommended by the vidhAna of shaunaka.
yAM kalpayanti no .arayaH krurAM kR^ityAM vadhumiva /
tAM brahmaNA .apanirnudmaH pratyak kartAramR^ichChatu //
This version is seen in the paippalAda saMhitA of the atharvaveda and is used in the kR^ityA destroying atharvanic rites and the tantric pratya~NgirA paddhatis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>mallaNNa</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/rudraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2007-06-24_a-local-pantheon-of-mallanna/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/rudraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2007-06-24_a-local-pantheon-of-mallanna/</guid>
      <description>(मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्लेखा काचित्। अत्र सौकर्यार्थं रक्षितम्।)
A train of thought culminated in me remembering the peculiar case of the equestrian deity mallaNNa found in Ailoni. There is a smaller temple of mallaNNa in that village. Here he is depicted with his two wives with four arms hold a sword, trident, skull bowl and Damaru. His first wife is mADaladevI who is supposed to be umA incarnated amongst the lingAyata-s or gone kApu-s.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Night of The god</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/rudraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-03-09_night-of-the-god/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/rudraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-03-09_night-of-the-god/</guid>
      <description>oM atitIkShNa mahAkAya kalpAntadahanopama jha~NkAra-bhairavAya namastubhyaM //
We invoke the fierce jha~NkAra-bhairava. We had worshipped the terrible god with the great litany, the mahAnyAsa on the great night that he may be pacified.
Having worshipped the great god we were reminded of the intriguing words of the illustrious Kashmirian Tantric abhinavagupta of shrinagara in his great work the tantrAloka (TA 15.264b-15.266):
na khalveSha shivaH shAnto nAma kashcidvibhedavAn // 264
sarvetarAdhvavyAvR^itto ghaTatulyo.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>rudra- his agents</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/rudraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2004-05-19_rudra-his-agents/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/rudraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2004-05-19_rudra-his-agents/</guid>
      <description>vIrabhadra: He emerged from a fragment of the matted locks of rudra for the killing of prajApati dakSha. He wrought havoc in the midsts of the deva armies and destroyed the demons created by bhR^igu before going on to behead dakSha. He then revived dakSha with a goat’s head.
kAla bhairava: Created by rudra for the beheading of the 5th head of brahma which was mocking rudra. For this he acquired the pApa of brahmahatyA and had to perform the kApAlika vrata.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>shUlinI</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/rudraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-04-19_shulini/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/rudraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-04-19_shulini/</guid>
      <description>The wings of sharabha are pratya~NgirA and shUlinI. shUlinI may be invoked to complement the invocation of pratya~NgirA. Her iconography is thus:
adhyArUDhAM mR^igendraM sajala-jaladhara-shyAmalAM hastapadmaiH shUlaM bANaM kR^ipANaM-ari-jalaja-gadA-chApa-pAshAn-vahantIM /
chandrottamsAM trinetrAM chatasR^ibhir-abhitaH kheTakAn bibhratIbhiH kanyAbhiH sevyamAnAM pratibhaTa-bhayadAM shUlinIM bhAvayAmi.
Her mantra may be combined with those of pratya~NgirA to rout the enemy. The mantra is provided as being:
jvala-jvala-padasyAnte shUlinIti padaM vadet /
duShTagrahaM humastrAnte vahnijAyAvadhirmanuH //
The R^iShi is dIrghatamA auchAthya the a~Ngiras, kakubh is the meter and samasta-sura-vanditA shUlinI devatA.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The chants of the rudra-s: a commentary based on our discussions</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/rudraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2008-11-09_the-chants-of-the-rudra-s-a-commentary-based-on-our-discussions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/rudraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2008-11-09_the-chants-of-the-rudra-s-a-commentary-based-on-our-discussions/</guid>
      <description>मानसतरङ्गिणीकृता लिखितम्। अत्र सौकर्याय रक्षितम्।
bhuvanasya pitaraM gIrbhir AbhI rudraM divA vardhayA rudram aktau |
bR^ihantaM R^iShvam ajaraM suShumnaM R^idhag-ghuvema kavineShitAsaH ||
With these chants we exalt rudra, the universe’s father, by day and by night;
We specially invoke him, bright, lofty, un-aging, and well-disposed, inspired by the wise one.
[kavi= the wise one, i.e. rudra. In modern tantrika parlance the suShumna mentioned in this R^ik is taken to mean the suShumna nerve path, but it is clear that in the vaidika context in simply meant well-disposed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The drinking of poison</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/rudraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2004-12-23_the-drinking-of-poison/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/rudraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2004-12-23_the-drinking-of-poison/</guid>
      <description>While the bhAgavataM is considered a vaiShNava text, it contains an highly magnified stotra to rudra. The stotra contains yet another example of the classical macrantropic motif that is so pervasive in Hindu thought since the puruSha sUktaM and the ashvamedha brAhmaNaM. It is full-fledged development was in India and not in Mesopotamia or Egypt. I provide a translation of the stotra given that the available ones are unsatisfactory.
shrI-prajApataya UchuH :/</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The praise of rudra</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/rudraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-02-22_the-praise-of-rudra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/rudraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-02-22_the-praise-of-rudra/</guid>
      <description>001 namas te deva-devesha devAri-balasUdana |
002 devendra-bala-viShTambha deva-dAnava-pUjita ||
Salutations to one who is lord of all the gods to the destroyer of the enemies of devas. One who is the inciter of the strength of the celestial chief. One who is adored by both gods and demons.
003 sahasrAkSha virUpAkSha tryakSha yakShAdhipa-priya |
004 sarvataH-pANi-pAdAnta sarvatokShishiromukha ||
One who is thousand-eyed, one who is many-eyed, and one who is three-eyed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The tale of the li~Nga</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/rudraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-11-22_the-tale-of-the-linga/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/rudraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-11-22_the-tale-of-the-linga/</guid>
      <description>The tale of the li~Nga as the phallus of shiva is found in several purANas and is hence not a late concotion. It can be traced back to the bhArgava redaction of the sauta literature. The following purANas state the story:
brahmANDa 1.2.27
kUrma 2.37
skanda 1.1.6, 7.1.187 and other references
vAmana 22.6.65
devIbhAgavata 4.20
shiva 4.12
The critical version of the core tale as can be reconstructed from the above sources goes thus:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>tripurAntaka brAhmaNa</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/rudraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2004-12-11_tripurantaka-brahmana/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/rudraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2004-12-11_tripurantaka-brahmana/</guid>
      <description>o3M teShAmsurANAM tisraH pura AsannayasmayyavamA.atha rajathA.atha hariNI tA devA jetuM nAshaknuvan tA upsadaivAjigIShan tasmAdAhuryashcaivaM veda yascha nopasadA vai mahApuraM jayanIti ta iShugaM samaskurvatAgnimanIkagaM somagaM shalyaM viShNum tejanaM te bruvan ka imAmasiShyatIti rudra ityabruvan rudro vai kruraH so.asyatviti so.abravIdvaraM vR^iNA ahameva pashUnAmadipatirasAnIti tasmAdrudraaH pashUnAmadipatistAgaM rudrovAsR^ijat sa tisraH puro bhittvaibhyo lokebhyo.asuran prANudate ||
The Asuras had three citadels; the lowest was of iron, then there was one of silver, then one of gold.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>trishiro-bhairava</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/rudraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-03-04_trishiro-bhairava/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/rudraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-03-04_trishiro-bhairava/</guid>
      <description>Images of the hallowed trishirobhairava from kAshmIr, whose avatAra puruSha is dattAtreya. These idols were originally from temples of trishiro bhairava near parihAsapura. They show the left side ugramukha which is (rudra murti) and may have a kapAla, kamaNDalu and akShamAla in the hands. The same iconography is retained for dattAtreya but, the kApAla of the trishirobhairava form is not seen. The temples were destroyed and the idols damaged by the Moslems and their current status is unclear.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>tumburu, the manifestation of rudra</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/rudraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-02-13_tumburu-the-manifestation-of-rudra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/rudraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-02-13_tumburu-the-manifestation-of-rudra/</guid>
      <description>From the northern head of the terrible rudra, known as the vAmadeva head, manifests the emanation of vAmadeva known as the four-faced tumburu surrounded by his 4 sisters. From the four faces of tumburu narrate the four great vAma tantras: 1) The frightening shirashCheda (also known as the jayadratha yAmala. 2) the terrific vINAshikA. 3) the mahAsaMmohana and 4) nayottara.
The shirashCheda tantra gives the following description of the tumburu emanation of vAmadeva:</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>