<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on संस्कारे विश्वासटिप्पणयः</title>
    <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/rudraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on संस्कारे विश्वासटिप्पणयः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
	<atom:link href="https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/rudraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>mallaNNa</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/rudraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2007-06-24_a-local-pantheon-of-mallanna/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/rudraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2007-06-24_a-local-pantheon-of-mallanna/</guid>
      <description>(मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्लेखा काचित्। अत्र सौकर्यार्थं रक्षितम्।)
A train of thought culminated in me remembering the peculiar case of the equestrian deity mallaNNa found in Ailoni. There is a smaller temple of mallaNNa in that village. Here he is depicted with his two wives with four arms hold a sword, trident, skull bowl and Damaru. His first wife is mADaladevI who is supposed to be umA incarnated amongst the lingAyata-s or gone kApu-s.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>rudra- his agents</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/rudraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2004-05-19_rudra-his-agents/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/rudraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2004-05-19_rudra-his-agents/</guid>
      <description>vIrabhadra: He emerged from a fragment of the matted locks of rudra for the killing of prajApati dakSha. He wrought havoc in the midsts of the deva armies and destroyed the demons created by bhR^igu before going on to behead dakSha. He then revived dakSha with a goat’s head.
kAla bhairava: Created by rudra for the beheading of the 5th head of brahma which was mocking rudra. For this he acquired the pApa of brahmahatyA and had to perform the kApAlika vrata.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The chants of the rudra-s: a commentary based on our discussions</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/rudraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2008-11-09_the-chants-of-the-rudra-s-a-commentary-based-on-our-discussions/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/rudraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2008-11-09_the-chants-of-the-rudra-s-a-commentary-based-on-our-discussions/</guid>
      <description>मानसतरङ्गिणीकृता लिखितम्। अत्र सौकर्याय रक्षितम्।
bhuvanasya pitaraM gIrbhir AbhI rudraM divA vardhayA rudram aktau |
bR^ihantaM R^iShvam ajaraM suShumnaM R^idhag-ghuvema kavineShitAsaH ||
With these chants we exalt rudra, the universe’s father, by day and by night;
We specially invoke him, bright, lofty, un-aging, and well-disposed, inspired by the wise one.
[kavi= the wise one, i.e. rudra. In modern tantrika parlance the suShumna mentioned in this R^ik is taken to mean the suShumna nerve path, but it is clear that in the vaidika context in simply meant well-disposed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>tumburu, the manifestation of rudra</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/rudraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-02-13_tumburu-the-manifestation-of-rudra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/rudraH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-02-13_tumburu-the-manifestation-of-rudra/</guid>
      <description>From the northern head of the terrible rudra, known as the vAmadeva head, manifests the emanation of vAmadeva known as the four-faced tumburu surrounded by his 4 sisters. From the four faces of tumburu narrate the four great vAma tantras: 1) The frightening shirashCheda (also known as the jayadratha yAmala. 2) the terrific vINAshikA. 3) the mahAsaMmohana and 4) nayottara.
The shirashCheda tantra gives the following description of the tumburu emanation of vAmadeva:</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>