<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on संस्कारे विश्वासटिप्पणयः</title>
    <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/viShNuH/meta/MT_lekhAH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on संस्कारे विश्वासटिप्पणयः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
	<atom:link href="https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/viShNuH/meta/MT_lekhAH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>ekAnamshA: a deity of tantric vaiShNavism</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/viShNuH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-02-04_ekanamsha-a-deity-of-tantric-vaishnavism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/viShNuH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-02-04_ekanamsha-a-deity-of-tantric-vaishnavism/</guid>
      <description>The core pantheon of the pA~ncharAtra texts is the chaturvyuha or the serial emanations of nArAyaNa. The primary manifestation of nArAyaNa is vAsudeva, from whom emerge saMkarShaNa and pradyumna. From pradyumna emerges aniruddha. This pantheon appears to be a unique feature of the yadu tribes that subsequently seems to have spawned the classical pA~ncharAtra. However, the early texts suggest that there was another parallel system that appears to have largely passed out of subsequent vaiShNavism.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>kShemendra on kalki</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/viShNuH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-03-03_kshemendra-on-kalki/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/viShNuH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-03-03_kshemendra-on-kalki/</guid>
      <description>The great Kashmirian author in his text the dashAvatAracharitra which was written in 1066 AD describes the conditions that would prevail on the earth just before the coming of kalki.
“The Turushkas, Pathans, Daradas and dwellers of Shakastan will cause the earth to decay as do the leper his open oozing sores. Every direction overrun by the dreadful mlechChas, the earth will resound with the clash of swords drawn in combat and her soil will be soaked with blood.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some speculation on the Indo-Aryan cult of the vasu-s</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/viShNuH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2009-11-10_some-speculation-on-the-indo-aryan-cult-of-the-vasu-s/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/viShNuH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2009-11-10_some-speculation-on-the-indo-aryan-cult-of-the-vasu-s/</guid>
      <description>मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्लेखा काचित्। अत्र सौकर्यार्थं रक्षितम्।
The below material arose as a collaborative venture in course of extended discussions with KR.

The winter solstice/year beginning in the last part of shraviShTha (1300 BCE)
The three great categories of gods in the veda and beyond Though absent in the extant Iranian texts, the oldest Indo-Aryan texts recognize the presence of three major categories of deva-s — the vasu-s, rudra-s and Aditya-s. This triad is mentioned on a number of occasions in the R^igveda.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>sudarshaNa rahasya</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/viShNuH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-07-18_sudarshana-rahasya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/viShNuH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-07-18_sudarshana-rahasya/</guid>
      <description>Having bowed to the one sleeping atop the coils of the snake of time we salute the greatest of his weapons.
oM urugAyAya hum phaT //
That supreme emanation of the shakti of nArAyaNa manifested with a predominance of her tejas, is as bright as many millions of suns, moons and fires in profusion. It pervades the tryambaka vidya of the 7th maNDala of the R^igveda. It is described as the supreme udyama, foremost prANa and all weapons and shaktis of the hordes of viShNu and vishvaksena arise from it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Buddhist kalki</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/viShNuH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-03-01_the-buddhist-kalki/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/viShNuH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-03-01_the-buddhist-kalki/</guid>
      <description>The bauddhas have internalized the last incarnation of viShNu, the all-destroying kalki or pramati who is said to annihilate the mlecchas and dasyus and restore the world to the Aryas. The kAlachakra tantra of the unclean upachInAchAra stream gives a highly remarkable account of the end of the yuga. It’s parallels to the mainstream Hindu version are unmistakable and appears to have been clearly derived from it [It is even possible that there was a now lost Hindu version which might have been a closer precursor of the version in the kAlachakra tantra].</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The chakras of viShNu</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/viShNuH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-02-14_the-chakras-of-vishnu/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/viShNuH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-02-14_the-chakras-of-vishnu/</guid>
      <description>From viShNu emanate several chakra missiles, all of which may follow the deadly sudarshana and discs when used in battle against the dAnavas and rAkShasas. They represent the sum of the deadly destructive fury of viShNu. Likewise, the sampUrNa chakra prayoga rite invokes these weapons to power the countering or attacking mantra missiles.
The following are the chakras:
1) mahArAtridhara chakra: This powered by mahAmAyA and is dark hued and terrifying with a single spoke.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The dark hero of the yadus</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/viShNuH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-08-27_the-dark-hero-of-the-yadus/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/viShNuH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-08-27_the-dark-hero-of-the-yadus/</guid>
      <description>The birth anniversary of the dark hero of the yadus dawned. We decided to
recall his awful deeds in course of his momentous life that overlapped with the tumult taking place in the bhArata realms.
-The yadu was born to vasudeva and devakI, who were imprisoned by kaMsa, devakI’s brother.The tyrant kaMsa had been told that devakI’s 8th son will kill him one day.
-devakI’s eighth son was born on a rohiNI aShtTami, and was spirited away by vasudeva to his cowherd friend nanda’s abode.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The left-handed aShTha-mukha gaNDabheruNDa nR^ikeshari mantra</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/viShNuH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-03-11_the-left-handed-ashtha-mukha-gandabherunda-nrikeshari-mantra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/viShNuH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-03-11_the-left-handed-ashtha-mukha-gandabherunda-nrikeshari-mantra/</guid>
      <description>It is said that there are two emanations of the mantra of the most terrible aShTha-mukha gaNDabheruNDa nR^isimha (AMGN)- a dakShiNa and vAma form. The right-handed form is said to lie in the text termed the bhIma-tantra which is a upa-tantra of the ananta-vijaya saMhitA of the viShNu-yAmala tradition. The left-handed form is said to like in the text termed vAmA-tantra which is also an upa-tantra of the ananta-vijaya saMhitA. Not much is know of the full extant of these texts ( if they survive in an degree at all they are obviously kept a close secret) but fragments relevant to ritual performance have been transmitted to those in the know.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The praise of varAha mUrtI</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/viShNuH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-03-12_the-praise-of-varaha-murti/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/viShNuH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-03-12_the-praise-of-varaha-murti/</guid>
      <description>daMShTrAyAM vasudhA sashaila-nagarAraNyApagA huMkR^itau vAgIshI shasite.anilo ravi vidhU bAhvoshcha dakShAnyayoH /
The earth with its mountains, cities, forests and waterbodies are in his tusks, his grunts are sarasvatI (vAgIshI). The air is his breath and the sun and moon are his right and left hands.
kukShau syurvasavo dishaH shrutipathe dasrau dR^ishoH pAdayoH padmottho hR^idaye hariH pR^ithagamI pujyA mukhe sha~NkaraH //
His belly is [made of] the vasus, in his ear are the directions, the ashvins are his eyes, in his feet is the lotus born [brahma], in his heart is viShNu and in his mouth is shiva.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The snake of viShNu</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/viShNuH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2004-12-06_the-snake-of-vishnu/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/viShNuH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2004-12-06_the-snake-of-vishnu/</guid>
      <description>Upon the great snake shesha sleeps the great god viShNu, even as the the kalpa wears out. He stirs only when the waters rise and threaten to sink the world plane. This shesha is time and hence he is called ananta. Thus, when viShNu sleeps on the coils of the great world snake he is experiencing the cyclic passage of time.
Once the great god vAyu and the world snake ananta had a contest of strength.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The vaiShNava mahAmantra</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/viShNuH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-10-16_the-vaishnava-mahamantra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/viShNuH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-10-16_the-vaishnava-mahamantra/</guid>
      <description>oM oM oM hrIM hrIM hrIM shrIM shrIM shrIM 0M aM aM aM hauM hauM hauM haMsaH haMsaH haMsaH oM hrIM shrIM namo viShNave //
The mantra rahasyas:
That great mantra encompasses a series of 3 praNavas. The 3 praNavas are the AdhAra that is known as the brahman. This is followed by the 3 tArikAs and the 3 anutArikAs which are two wives of viShNu. They are the supremre states with all things existing in these two shaktis of viShNu.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>vibhavas of viShNu</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/viShNuH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-03-10_vibhavas-of-vishnu/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/viShNuH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-03-10_vibhavas-of-vishnu/</guid>
      <description>The vibhavas:
padmanAbha
dhruva
ananta
shaktIsha
madhusudhana
vidyAdhideva
kapila
vishvarUpa
haMsa
krodAtman
vaDavaktra
dharma
vAgIshvara
ekArNavashaya
kUrma
varAha
nR^isimha
amR^itAharaNA
shripati
kAntAtman
rAhujit
kAlanemighna
pArijAtahara
lokanAtha
dattAtreya
nygrodashAyin
ekashR^i~Ngatanu
vAmana
trivikrama
nara
nArAyaNa
hari
kR^iShNa
rAmo bhArgava
rAmachandra
vyAsa
kalkI
pAtAlashAyin</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>