<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on संस्कारे विश्वासटिप्पणयः</title>
    <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/skandaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on संस्कारे विश्वासटिप्पणयः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
	<atom:link href="https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/skandaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>ShaShTi</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/skandaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2004-06-06_shashti/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/skandaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2004-06-06_shashti/</guid>
      <description>ShaShTi is the wife of the terrible 6-headed lord of the bhUtas. She is the daughter of yama or indra. When grandson of manu was still-born he was revived by the great ShaShTi. She is also known as devasenA or senA and is worshipped on the shri pa~nchamI, the 5th day after dIpAvali. A tarpaNaM performed to her and kumAra with the mantras from the bodhAyana dharmasUtra. Usually the tarpaNaM is performed under a large ashvatta tree or some other tree.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>skanda vara</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/skandaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-03-18_skanda-vara/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/skandaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-03-18_skanda-vara/</guid>
      <description>The boons offered by the deity kumAra are of great certainty, but they be extremely perplexing and their good result may only be seen after some ironic hardship undergone by the recepient. Hence is he known as the roguish dhUrta, who composed the taskara vidyA by manifesting as kanakahastin and bhAskaranandin. But even the paths to the attainment of chaurya perfection were not straight. amba wanted to slay bhIShma for which she received a garland from kumAra but none ever wore it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The roguish Karttikeya and the wives of the gods</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/skandaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2004-08-02_the-roguish-karttikeya-and-the-wives-of-the-gods/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/skandaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2004-08-02_the-roguish-karttikeya-and-the-wives-of-the-gods/</guid>
      <description>We worship the roguish deity kumAra with offerings as ordained by the school of the great sage gopatha.
Due to the efficiency of the law enforcement and strictures of the dharma shAstra the rogues and thieves of the land were no longer able achieving their aims. So the rogues and thieves decided to worship the great spear-wielding deity who is known to some as son of agni, to others as the first born son of the fierce rudra and to yet other as the son of the kR^ittikA-s.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The secret of sumukhI</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/skandaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-04-07_the-secret-of-sumukhi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/skandaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-04-07_the-secret-of-sumukhi/</guid>
      <description>The great deva sanatkumAra, the son of the fiery agni, is always in the company of his two wives: the glorious biDAlAkShi and the wonderous sumukhI. The one who knows this rahasya and performs the invocation of sumukhI along with the great dhUrtasvamI will be favored by them. That glorious goddess sumukhI also called the great mahAmayUrI, engaged in amorous dalliance with the dhUrta, is described as sulabhAgati. In the midst of her yantra, the mate of kArttikeya is meditated as residing and invoked with the mighty mantra (in mantra shAstra code):</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The wives of Mars and the Carmen Arvale</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/skandaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2008-10-04_the-wives-of-mars/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/skandaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2008-10-04_the-wives-of-mars/</guid>
      <description>मानसतरङ्गिणीकृता लिखितम्। अत्र सौकर्याय रक्षितम्।
In our earlier discussion we had argued based on structural homologies the marut-s of the vedic system are “para-skanda”. We speculated that kumAra himself descends from a para-vedic Indo-Iranian system, which contained an ancestral version of the deity, who in that system was the homolog of the marut-s of the vedic system. This para-vedic skanda was laterally transferred to the vedic system in the late vedic period of India.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>