<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on संस्कारे विश्वासटिप्पणयः</title>
    <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/skandaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on संस्कारे विश्वासटिप्पणयः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
	<atom:link href="https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/skandaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>kumAra vidyA-s</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/skandaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-10-10_kumara-vidya-s/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/skandaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-10-10_kumara-vidya-s/</guid>
      <description>Of the mUrti-s of kumAra [Note 1] that are worshiped by the educated kaumAra sAdhaka there are few having a special significance.
ajArUDha The first of these is of great import for a dvija devoted the yAj~nIkI perfection. It is the form known as ajArUDha. Here the great lord of the beautiful ShaShThi is meditated upon in the bindu of the maNDala thus:
dvimukhaM chAShTa-bahuM cha shvetaM vA shyAMa-skandharaM |</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ShaShTi</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/skandaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2004-06-06_shashti/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/skandaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2004-06-06_shashti/</guid>
      <description>ShaShTi is the wife of the terrible 6-headed lord of the bhUtas. She is the daughter of yama or indra. When grandson of manu was still-born he was revived by the great ShaShTi. She is also known as devasenA or senA and is worshipped on the shri pa~nchamI, the 5th day after dIpAvali. A tarpaNaM performed to her and kumAra with the mantras from the bodhAyana dharmasUtra. Usually the tarpaNaM is performed under a large ashvatta tree or some other tree.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>skanda gaNas</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/skandaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-07-23_skanda-ganas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/skandaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-07-23_skanda-ganas/</guid>
      <description>Weighed down by the arrows showered by our foes, we call upon son of the ranger of kailAsha. He who bears the bow in battle and showers arrows on the dAnava horde. He who is called ugratama and bhImatama, who rushes to battle with the the axe and spear, we worship him in the midst of the six-fold maNDala. One who is dallying with sumukhi and biDAlAkShI, we bow to him.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>skanda vara</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/skandaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-03-18_skanda-vara/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/skandaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-03-18_skanda-vara/</guid>
      <description>The boons offered by the deity kumAra are of great certainty, but they be extremely perplexing and their good result may only be seen after some ironic hardship undergone by the recepient. Hence is he known as the roguish dhUrta, who composed the taskara vidyA by manifesting as kanakahastin and bhAskaranandin. But even the paths to the attainment of chaurya perfection were not straight. amba wanted to slay bhIShma for which she received a garland from kumAra but none ever wore it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The AkhyAna of skanda-patnI</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/skandaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-10-19_the-akhyana-of-skanda-patni/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/skandaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-10-19_the-akhyana-of-skanda-patni/</guid>
      <description>OM hrIM ShaShaThI devyai svAhA ||
The wandering sUta said: “Listen to the wonderous AkhyAna of skanda-patnI that relieves unborn and young kids from troubles. In days long past I was wandering in the fringes of the magadha, when I stumbled into the mighty brahmin, kashyapa, the son of marIchI. I asked him to narrate to me the tale of the wonderous exploits of skanda and his agents.
kashyapa said: “Listen sUta this ancient story of the great god kumAra, the commander of the deva forces and his agents.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The deadly foe-destroying yoga of brahmaNya deva</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/skandaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2004-09-12_the-deadly-foe-destroying-yoga-of-brahmanya-deva/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/skandaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2004-09-12_the-deadly-foe-destroying-yoga-of-brahmanya-deva/</guid>
      <description>“We pacify the six-headed being, of fiery birth, who is lost in the embrace of the beautiful daughter of the god of the gods indra. May his lethal darts not harm us and instead strike our foes.”
At the heart of the kaumara tantric rite lies the great secret yoga which destroys ones foes. The skandArchana kalpadruma and other obscure kaumAra texts refer to this secret yoga, the configuration of the incantation for which is normally revealed only by oral tradition.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The kaumAra vidyA</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/skandaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-01-16_the-kaumara-vidya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/skandaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-01-16_the-kaumara-vidya/</guid>
      <description>Having paid respect with to rAja bhojadeva, who stands in the line of the teachers from ShaShThinAtha we salute the god who is in the embrace of sUryasunuduhitR^i.
The cryptic mantra goes thus:
vAk (holy speech) is the varman (armour)
the karNabindvADhya (ear ornaments) go with the charama (last one)
The Fish banner flutters (mInaketana)
salutations to kumAra.
We also worship that awful being, riding a horse or a violent elephant, embracing pUrNA and puShkalA along with his hosts like goptR^i</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The mahA-kumAra-rahasya</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/skandaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-11-18_the-maha-kumara-rahasya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/skandaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-11-18_the-maha-kumara-rahasya/</guid>
      <description>The great rahasya of the 6-headed one goes thus:
1) First there is the praNava, which encompasses the akSharas from shrIkaNTha the father of the young god to the last of the pentads of brahman.
2) kAmarUpaM vahnyArUDhaM bindumAlinIbhuShitaM kAlabindumilitaM (the first core bIja)
3) tryashraM yoniH (the 2nd core bIja)
4) tritIya [tithi] iti ichChA ( the 3rd core bIja)
5) unmeSha (the 4th core bIja)
6) AkAsha tattvaM cha anuttaraM (5th core bIja)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The roguish Karttikeya and the wives of the gods</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/skandaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2004-08-02_the-roguish-karttikeya-and-the-wives-of-the-gods/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/skandaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2004-08-02_the-roguish-karttikeya-and-the-wives-of-the-gods/</guid>
      <description>We worship the roguish deity kumAra with offerings as ordained by the school of the great sage gopatha.
Due to the efficiency of the law enforcement and strictures of the dharma shAstra the rogues and thieves of the land were no longer able achieving their aims. So the rogues and thieves decided to worship the great spear-wielding deity who is known to some as son of agni, to others as the first born son of the fierce rudra and to yet other as the son of the kR^ittikA-s.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The second circle</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/skandaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-05-08_the-second-circle/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/skandaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-05-08_the-second-circle/</guid>
      <description>We had sought she who dwells in the midst of the kiri chakra. Our AchArya’s AchArya the one learned in the great atharvan lore with all its parishiShTha-s, kalpa-s brAhmaNa and upaniShads retired to live in the most picturesque land south of lATa pradesha, with forests largely inhabited by niShAda tribes. There on the banks of the Damanganga river he settled down with the forest providing him the quietude and oShadhI-s for his rites.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The secret of sumukhI</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/skandaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-04-07_the-secret-of-sumukhi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/skandaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-04-07_the-secret-of-sumukhi/</guid>
      <description>The great deva sanatkumAra, the son of the fiery agni, is always in the company of his two wives: the glorious biDAlAkShi and the wonderous sumukhI. The one who knows this rahasya and performs the invocation of sumukhI along with the great dhUrtasvamI will be favored by them. That glorious goddess sumukhI also called the great mahAmayUrI, engaged in amorous dalliance with the dhUrta, is described as sulabhAgati. In the midst of her yantra, the mate of kArttikeya is meditated as residing and invoked with the mighty mantra (in mantra shAstra code):</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The wives of Mars and the Carmen Arvale</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/skandaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2008-10-04_the-wives-of-mars/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/skandaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2008-10-04_the-wives-of-mars/</guid>
      <description>मानसतरङ्गिणीकृता लिखितम्। अत्र सौकर्याय रक्षितम्।
In our earlier discussion we had argued based on structural homologies the marut-s of the vedic system are “para-skanda”. We speculated that kumAra himself descends from a para-vedic Indo-Iranian system, which contained an ancestral version of the deity, who in that system was the homolog of the marut-s of the vedic system. This para-vedic skanda was laterally transferred to the vedic system in the late vedic period of India.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>vedic mantra-s adapted for kaumAra ritual</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/skandaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-10-18_vedic-mantras-adapted-for-kaumara-ritual/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/mantraH/skandaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-10-18_vedic-mantras-adapted-for-kaumara-ritual/</guid>
      <description>kumAram mAtA yuvatiH samubdhaM guhA bibharti na dadAti pitre |
anIkam asya na minaj janAsaH puraH pashyanti nihitam aratau ||
**The young mother keeps the boy hidden in secret, nor gives him to the father;
Men see his undiminishing radiance only when he is set up on the fuel sticks [reeds].
In the vedic context it refers to agni hidden within his “mother”: the kindling wood block, who is hidden away from the father: the fire-drill.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>