<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on संस्कारे विश्वासटिप्पण्यः</title>
    <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/AgamaH/vaiShNavaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;मानसतरङ्गिणीकृल्-लेखाः on संस्कारे विश्वासटिप्पण्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
	<atom:link href="https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/AgamaH/vaiShNavaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>A note on the vaikhAnasa tradition</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/AgamaH/vaiShNavaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-02-16_a-note-on-the-vaikhanasa-tradition/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/AgamaH/vaiShNavaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-02-16_a-note-on-the-vaikhanasa-tradition/</guid>
      <description>The vaikhAnasas appear to represent an archaic branch of vaiShNavas who are distinct from the more popular and numerous pA~ncharAtrins. The vaikhAnasas however were and are still influential in few south Indian temples including the world’s most famous shrine, venkaTAdri (Other examples being the viShNu temple of vANamAmalai). The vaikhAnasas belong to a kR^iShNa yajurvedic shAkhA founded by the descendent of the ancient R^iShi of the A~Ngirasa clan, vikhAnas. The vaikhAnasas seem to have adopted a form of vaiShnavism early on, and are probably even amongst the earliest of the vaiShNavas alluded to in the nArAyaNIya section of the mahAbhArata.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ekAnaMshA in nAstIka myth-making and implications for AstIka Paurano-Tantric history</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/AgamaH/vaiShNavaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-11-01_ekanamsha-in-nastika-myth-making-and-implications-for-astika-paurano-tantric-history/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/AgamaH/vaiShNavaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-11-01_ekanamsha-in-nastika-myth-making-and-implications-for-astika-paurano-tantric-history/</guid>
      <description>nAstika take Context buddhagosha declared that the bauddha zealots should not listen to public narratives of the rAmAyaNa or mahAbhArata that the Astikas delight in. Yet, the nAstikas both jaina and bauddha have their own versions of several core narratives and branching AkhyAnas found in the canonical itihAsa and purANa literature of the Astikas. One striking feature is that their versions differ strikingly from the Astika versions. The bauddha ones, typically, are even more divergent than the jaina ones.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>lakShmI tantraM</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/AgamaH/vaiShNavaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2004-02-09_lakshmi-tantram/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/AgamaH/vaiShNavaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2004-02-09_lakshmi-tantram/</guid>
      <description>One of the most lucid expositions of the foundational philosophy of pA~ncharatra is seen in the lecture given by lakShmI to indra in the lakShmI-tantraM (chapter 4):
1) Originally lakShmI and viShNu are conjoined in an undifferentiated form termed the “pure space”. This combination of viShNu and shrI is termed the homogeneous state which cannot be discerned and with out any fluctuations in it.
2) From time to time a minute particle comprising of a 10^-18 viShNu-shrI continuum state differentiates into action.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>List of pA~ncharatra tantra-s</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/AgamaH/vaiShNavaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-06-01_list-of-pancharatra-tantra-s/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/AgamaH/vaiShNavaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-06-01_list-of-pancharatra-tantra-s/</guid>
      <description>With the muni, the shrI vaiShNava and R’s father we have made a comprehensive list of pA~ncharAtra tantras that are supposed to have existed. We simply have little to no details of many of them and cannot say much about their existence. Of others only fragments are known from manuscripts or citations or prayoga traditions. Several purported saMhitA-s that are recorded based on citations are spurious and are seem to be vedic saMhitA-s or kalpa texts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on early pAncharAtra vaiShNavism</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/AgamaH/vaiShNavaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-03-27_notes-on-early-pancharatra-vaishnavism/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/AgamaH/vaiShNavaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-03-27_notes-on-early-pancharatra-vaishnavism/</guid>
      <description>It is likely that in the later period the vaiShNavas were ignorant on why the name pA~ncharatra came into being. This ignorance of the meaning of the name is plainly seen in the explanation provided by the prashna saMhitA and padma saMhitA of pA~ncharAtra, and the nAradIya pA~ncharAtra has only a vague memory regarding the cause of the name.
The kashmirAcharyas of mahAbala paNDita’s school and vidyAraNya yati cite a number of formulae of pA~ncharAtra vaiShNavism.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The lineage of the viShNu tantras</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/AgamaH/vaiShNavaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-08-06_the-lineage-of-the-vishnu-tantras/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/AgamaH/vaiShNavaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2005-08-06_the-lineage-of-the-vishnu-tantras/</guid>
      <description>oM ugraM vIraM mahAviShNuM jvalantaM sarvatomukhaM |
nR^isiMhaM bhIShaNaM bhadraM mR^ityu-mR^ityaM namAmyahaM ||
How did these mightiest mantras of viShNu come into being? Beyond pa~ncharAtra promulgated by the chitrashikaNDins are the tantras of viShNu made apparent by the shANDilyas. The root tantra of these is the glorious viShNu yAmala. From here stem the ugra viShNu, halAyudha, ugrachakra and other formulations. After bhairava had been quenched by the draught of viShNu’s blood he asked sadAshiva to narrate the glorious vidyAs of viShNu.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The sarvAtman hymn to viShNu</title>
      <link>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/AgamaH/vaiShNavaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-12-31_the-sarvatman-hymn-to-vishnu/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vvasuki.github.io/saMskAra/AgamaH/vaiShNavaH/meta/MT_lekhAH/2006-12-31_the-sarvatman-hymn-to-vishnu/</guid>
      <description>The sarvAtmAn hymn to viShNu shows some variations between recensions and traditions but form accepted amongst smArtas has 40 core shlokas corresponding to Mbh 12.47.23-63. This an extremely important hymn of viShNu, comparable to the hymn to rudra by the goat-faced dakSha. The R^iShi of sarvAtmaka mahAvaiShNava stotra is given as bhagavAn vyAsa, the Chandas is anuShTubh, the devAtA is sarvAtmaka mahA-viShNu.
Its importance lies in the fact that it might represent one of the earliest post-vedic compositions to viShNu, within an early vaiShNava lineage that was strongly affiliated with vedic ritualism.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>